Alright, so we're back to Scala@Lightspeed.
さて、Scala@Lightspeedに戻ってきたよ。
So I just mentioned in the previous video that the Scala@Lightspeed mini-course is closing,
前回の動画でScala@Lightspeedミニコースはもうすぐ終わりって言ったけど、
and here I am with another lesson.
もう一つレッスンがあるんだ。
This is Daniel for Rock the JVM, and in this video I'll show you contextual abstractions
Rock the JVMのDanielだよ。この動画ではコンテキスト抽象（contextual abstractions）を
specifically in Scala 3.
Scala 3に特化して紹介するよ。
The rest of the mini-course works just fine on both Scala 2 and Scala 3, and in this video
ミニコースの他のレッスンはScala 2でもScala 3でも問題なく動くけど、この動画では
we're going to write specific Scala 3.
Scala 3専用のコードを書いていくよ。
So let's move back to our project, and under com.rockthejvm I'm going to create another
じゃあプロジェクトに戻って、com.rockthejvmの下に新しい
Scala application, I'm going to name this contextual abstractions, and I'm going to
Scalaアプリケーションを作ろう。名前はcontextual abstractionsにして、
make it an object as before, just in case we need to test something, and I'm going to add
前と同じようにobjectにしておこう。テスト用にね。あと、
a main method.
mainメソッドも追加するよ。
Now make sure that your project is specifically set up with Scala 3, which you can find here
プロジェクトがScala 3でセットアップされてることを確認してね。
under build.sbt, or you can go to, I think it's file, and then project structure, and here
build.sbtで確認できるし、FileメニューからProject Structureを開けば、
you'll find the Scala version that you created your project with.
プロジェクトのScalaバージョンが確認できるよ。
So let me collapse my file explorer, and let me show you what I mean by contextual abstractions.
じゃあファイルエクスプローラーを閉じて、コンテキスト抽象ってどういうことか見せるね。
This lesson will have two big techniques that will give Scala some extra power and extra
このレッスンでは、Scalaにさらなるパワーと
expressiveness.
表現力を与える2つの大きなテクニックを紹介するよ。
The first set of features is called context parameters, or arguments, and I'm going to
最初の機能はコンテキストパラメータ、またはコンテキスト引数って呼ばれるもので、
show you shortly what I mean by that, and this will also motivate the name of contextual abstractions,
すぐにどういう意味か見せるよ。これを見ればコンテキスト抽象っていう名前の意味もわかるはず。
which is quite vague, but frankly, I couldn't find a better name myself.
まあ正直かなり曖昧な名前だけど、自分でもこれ以上いい名前が思いつかなかったんだよね。
So I'm going to start with a simple example, I'm going to define a small list, let's call
じゃあ簡単な例から始めよう。小さなリストを定義するよ。
this a list, and I'm going to create a list of numbers, and I'm going to specifically enter
aListって名前にして、数字のリストを作るんだけど、わざと
them in a different order than the ascending ones.
昇順じゃない順番で入れるよ。
So I'm going to say two, one, three, four, or something like that.
2、1、3、4みたいな感じでね。
Now, the list data structure, much like most sequences in the Scala standard library, has
Listデータ構造には、Scala標準ライブラリの他のシーケンスと同じように、
a method called sorted.
sortedっていうメソッドがあるんだ。
So I'm going to say, let's call this an ordered list.
anOrderedListって名前にしよう。
I'm going to say list.sorted.
list.sortedって書くよ。
Now, sorted doesn't take any arguments, but if I print line the ordered list, and if you
sortedは引数を取らないんだけど、このanOrderedListをprintlnして、
run this application, it'll take a couple of seconds for this thing to compile, we'll
アプリケーションを実行すると、コンパイルに数秒かかるけど、
get the list one, two, three, four.
List(1, 2, 3, 4)が得られるよ。
And the list is magically sorted in ascending order, as if the compiler knew by magic what
リストが魔法のように昇順にソートされてる。まるでコンパイラが
the natural ordering of ints should be.
Intの自然な順序を魔法で知ってるかのようにね。
Now, from your existing programming experience, you may have done a bit of sorting of collections
プログラミング経験がある人なら、コレクションのソートを
yourself, and you probably are aware that whenever you want to sort a collection, maybe a list,
やったことがあると思う。コレクションをソートするときには、リストでも
or an array, or what have you, you need to pass some sort of comparison function.
配列でも何でも、何らかの比較関数を渡す必要があるよね。
So something like a comparator or object, or have the elements be comparable themselves,
コンパレータオブジェクトとか、要素自体がComparableだったり、
or some other form of telling the runtime which element is "less than" another element,
あるいは何かしらの方法で、ある要素が別の要素より「小さい」ことを
so that we know which element needs to stay first, and which element needs to stay last in the
ランタイムに教えてあげないといけない。どの要素が先に来て、
sorted collection.
どの要素が後ろに来るかを決めるためにね。
Now, in Scala, we have an existing comparison function, or comparison object, and that is
Scalaには既存の比較関数、比較オブジェクトがあって、
called ordering.
それがOrderingだよ。
Now, an ordering is pretty much a glorified two argument function that says which element
Orderingは基本的に、どの要素がどの要素より小さいかを示す
is less than another element.
2引数関数を豪華にラップしたものなんだ。
So, I can define, for example, descending ordering as ordering of int, and the type ordering comes
例えばdescendingOrderingをOrdering[Int]として定義できる。Ordering型は
predefined in the Scala standard library, and I can build an ordering object by saying ordering
Scala標準ライブラリにあらかじめ定義されてて、Ordering.fromLessThanで
from less than, so you're basically wrapping a two argument function that returns a boolean,
Orderingオブジェクトを作れるよ。つまりBooleanを返す2引数関数をラップするんだ。
and the boolean says the first element is smaller than the second element, with "smaller than"
そのBooleanは「最初の要素が2番目の要素より小さい」ことを表す。
in air quotes.
まあ「小さい」はカッコ付きだけどね。
So, I'm gonna say, for example, underscore, greater than, underscore.
で、例えば _ > _ って書くよ。
So, this is the shorthand lambda notation in Scala that you may have seen in the previous
これは前の動画で見たScalaのラムダの省略記法で、
video, so that's essentially a, b, arrow, a bigger than b.
(a, b) => a > b と同じ意味だよ。
So I'm basically saying that given to elements a and b, a is "less than b", so a should stay
つまり要素aとbがあったとき、aがbより「小さい」、つまりaがbの前に来るのは、
before b, if a is greater than b in the mathematical sense, alright?
aが数学的な意味でbより大きいとき、ってことだね。
So this is what the ordering object will do, and here in this lambda, you can define your
これがOrderingオブジェクトの役割で、このラムダの中で
own logic for comparing numbers.
数値の比較ロジックを自由に定義できるんだ。
Now, the thing is that the compiler can automatically sort a list by having access to some value of
ポイントは、コンパイラがScala標準ライブラリに組み込まれた
ordering int that comes pre-built with the Scala standard library.
Ordering[Int]の値にアクセスして、自動的にリストをソートできるってこと。
So this instance of ordering int, which denotes the natural ordering of integers, is automatically
つまり整数の自然な順序を表すOrdering[Int]のインスタンスが、
fetched by the compiler somehow, and injected into the argument of the sorted method.
コンパイラによって自動的に取得されて、sortedメソッドの引数に注入されるんだ。
So we say sorted, but in reality, it actually has an additional argument that has an ordering
sortedって書くだけだけど、実際にはOrderingを受け取る追加の引数があって、
which is automatically injected by the compiler.
それがコンパイラによって自動的に注入されてるんだよ。
Now in order to be able to inject our own ordering into the sorted method of list, we are going
で、自分のOrderingをListのsortedメソッドに注入したい場合は、
to make this descending ordering thing, or whatever ordering we might want to use for the sorted
このdescendingOrdering、あるいはsortedに使いたい任意のOrderingを
method, and we're going to make it a given.
givenにすればいいんだ。
Now a given instance will be automatically fetched by the compiler for every single method that
givenインスタンスは、Ordering[Int]型のいわゆる魔法のファントム引数を
takes a so-called magical phantom argument here, of type ordering int.
取るすべてのメソッドに対して、コンパイラが自動的に取得してくれるよ。
So in this case, for a list.sorted, the compiler will not fetch the given ordering of int, which
だからこの場合、list.sortedでコンパイラはScala標準ライブラリの
is the natural ordering of integers built in from the Scala standard library, but it will rather
整数の自然な順序を表すgivenのOrdering[Int]ではなく、
use this given instance that I've defined.
自分が定義したこのgivenインスタンスを使ってくれる。
So this will actually be injected with the descending ordering that I have defined here in this scope.
つまりこのスコープで定義した降順のOrderingが実際に注入されるんだ。
So if I run this application again, we're going to see the list sorted backwards this time
だからもう一度アプリケーションを実行すると、今度はリストが逆順に
around.
ソートされるよ。
So we see list 4321.
List(4, 3, 2, 1)だね。
So this is quite magical.
これはなかなか魔法っぽいでしょ。
Depending on the kind of given instances that we define in the scope where a method with these
メソッドが呼ばれるスコープでどんなgivenインスタンスを定義するかによって、
kinds of arguments is being called, we can change the behavior of that method.
そのメソッドの振る舞いを変えることができるんだ。
Now the phantom argument to the sorted method is actually called a contextual argument.
sortedメソッドのこのファントム引数は、正式にはコンテキスト引数って呼ばれるよ。
So sorted actually takes an argument list, but that argument list contains an element or an
sortedは実は引数リストを取るんだけど、その引数リストにはOrdering[Int]型の
instance of type ordering int, which is contextual.
要素が含まれてて、これがコンテキスト依存なんだ。
So depending on the context where the sorted method is being called, the compiler will fetch
sortedメソッドが呼ばれるコンテキストに応じて、コンパイラは
whatever given instance it has access to within that scope.
そのスコープ内でアクセスできるgivenインスタンスを取得する。
And with that ordering int, the behavior of sorted will give you back different results.
そのOrdering[Int]次第で、sortedの結果が変わるってわけ。
So if I had not created this given instance, then if I run this application again, the compiler
もしこのgivenインスタンスを作ってなかったら、アプリを実行すると、
will fetch whatever given instance it may have access to from the Scala standard library.
コンパイラはScala標準ライブラリからアクセスできるgivenインスタンスを取得する。
So we get list 1234 from the natural ordering of integers.
だから整数の自然な順序でList(1, 2, 3, 4)が返ってくるよ。
If I create my instance of descending ordering with my own logic, then the behavior of sorted
自分のロジックで降順のOrderingインスタンスを作れば、
changes and we get the list sorted backwards.
sortedの振る舞いが変わって、リストが逆順にソートされるんだ。
Now, if you want to make an analogy to the previous video where we talked about implicits, a given
前の動画でimplicitについて話したけど、それとの対比で言うと、
instance is analogous to an implicit vowel.
givenインスタンスはimplicit valと同じようなものだよ。
And because the Scala 3 standard library is still very young and implicits are going to
Scala 3の標準ライブラリはまだ若くて、implicitは
be deprecated in future versions of Scala 3.
将来のScala 3のバージョンで非推奨になる予定なんだ。
The sorted method takes an implicit value of ordering B. So this will be the phantom argument,
sortedメソッドはimplicit値としてOrdering[B]を取る。これがファントム引数、
the contextual argument that I mentioned here that you can solve or that you can pass automatically
つまりコンテキスト引数で、sortedメソッドが呼ばれるスコープに
through the compiler by creating a given instance of ordering in in the scope where the sorted method
Ordering[Int]のgivenインスタンスを作ることで、
is being called.
コンパイラに自動的に渡させることができるんだ。
Now, in Scala 3, you have the ultimate freedom to choose whether your methods that you want
Scala 3では、自分のビジネスロジックのメソッドに
to implement in your business logic will support this sort of behavior that will take contextual
この種の振る舞い、つまりコンテキスト引数を取って
arguments and having different behaviors depending on the scope or the context where they're called.
呼び出しスコープやコンテキストに応じて動作が変わるようにするかどうか、完全に自由に選べるよ。
Let me give an example.
例を見せるね。
So I'm going to define a trait, I'm going to call this combinator, and I'm going to type it
traitを定義しよう。Combinatorって名前にして、型引数Aを持たせる。
with the type argument a, and this combinator has a simple method called combine.
このCombinatorにはcombineっていうシンプルなメソッドがあって、
And it will combine two elements of type a, so x of type a and y of type a, and it will
A型の2つの要素xとyを取って、
return another element of type a.
A型の別の要素を返すよ。
Now, an example of combinator would be something that sums two integers together and returns
Combinatorの例としては、2つの整数を足し合わせて
their mathematical sum.
数学的な合計を返すものがあるね。
Now, technically, mathematically, this is called a monoid, but I'm going to revert to the combinator
厳密に言えば数学的にはモノイドって呼ばれるけど、
name because it's much more descriptive.
Combinatorの方がわかりやすいからこの名前にするよ。
Now, assume that I'm going to define a method called combineAll that takes a type argument
じゃあcombineAllっていうメソッドを定義しよう。型引数Aを取って、
a, and a list, which is a list of a, and this returns an a, which is the result of collapsing
listはList[A]で、Aを返す。特定のCombinatorのロジックで
all the elements of the list into the same value given by the logic of a particular combinator.
リストの全要素を一つの値に畳み込んだ結果だね。
So I'm going to pass a combinator here as a second argument.
2番目の引数としてCombinatorを渡すよ。
So I'm going to say combinator as a combinator a.
combinator: Combinator[A]って書く。
Now when you write something like this, in practice, there are several wishes involved in
実際にこういうメソッドを書くとき、いくつか望みが出てくるんだ。
such methods.
こういうメソッドにはね。
First of all, your API, this combineAll, might get quite big and quite cumbersome and boilerplate-y
まず、このcombineAllっていうAPIは、呼び出し側でかなり大きくて
at the call site.
面倒くさくなりがちなんだ。
So whenever you want to actually use combineAll on a bunch of lists, you always have to pass
combineAllを使うたびに、毎回その型に合った正しいCombinatorを
the right combinators of those particular types.
渡さないといけない。
And especially if you use this often, this might get quite annoying.
頻繁に使う場合、これはかなりうっとうしくなるよね。
The second wish is that you might simply want to not care what the local combinator rules
2つ目の望みは、呼び出し側でのローカルなCombinatorのルールを
are at the call site of combineAll.
いちいち気にしたくないってこと。
So you might want to ideally call combineAll on the list 1234 and not really care what the
理想的にはcombineAllをList(1, 2, 3, 4)に対して呼んで、
combination logic will be for the call site here.
結合ロジックが何かなんて気にしたくないよね。
Maybe you're doing some math library and combineAll for list 1234 naturally sums them together.
数学ライブラリを作ってるなら、List(1, 2, 3, 4)のcombineAllは自然に合計するはず。
You don't really need to pass a combinator which sums up all the integers every single time.
毎回整数を合計するCombinatorを渡す必要なんてないよね。
Now this may sound like a first world problem.
贅沢な悩みに聞こえるかもしれないけど、
But in reality, this kind of call or this kind of code would actually quite dramatically improve
実際にはこの種のコードは、コードの品質と
the quality of your code and the quality of your development life.
開発体験をかなり劇的に向上させるんだ。
So in order to be able to grant this kind of wishes, then we would add a context argument
こういう望みを叶えるために、このcombineAllメソッドに
here to this combineAll method.
コンテキスト引数を追加するよ。
So we would make the combinator a be a contextual argument by using a keyword called using.
Combinator[A]をusingキーワードを使ってコンテキスト引数にするんだ。
So when you say using combinator as combinator a, the compiler will need to take care to pass
using combinator: Combinator[A]って書くと、combineAllを呼ぶときに
the appropriate combinator a whenever you call combineAll if you have a given of that type
スコープにその型のgivenがあれば、コンパイラが適切なCombinator[A]を
in scope.
自動的に渡してくれるよ。
So I'm going to show you how you can use that shortly.
すぐに使い方を見せるね。
Let's implement this real quick.
じゃあ実装しよう。
So I'm going to say list.reduce and I'm going to pass a two argument function that is based
list.reduceにCombinatorベースの2引数関数を渡すよ。
on the combiner.
combinator.combineだね。
So I'm going to say combinator.combine.
combinator.combineって書く。
Or if you prefer the long hand notation, I can say a, b, arrow, combinator combine with
長い書き方にするなら、(a, b) => combinator.combine(a, b)
a and b.
って感じ。
All right.
OK。
So I can say list.reduce on this lambda.
list.reduceにこのラムダを渡せばいい。
And this lambda will take care to collapse this entire list under the combination function
このラムダがCombinatorの結合関数を使って
of the combinator.
リスト全体を畳み込んでくれるよ。
Now this structure with the context argument does two things.
このコンテキスト引数の構造は2つのことをしてくれる。
Let's say that I define the sum of all the numbers in a list.
リスト内の全数値の合計を定義してみよう。
And I'm going to call combineAll.
combineAllを呼ぶよ。
So combineAll of that particular list that I defined at the beginning.
最初に定義したリストに対してcombineAllする。
So I'm going to say combineAll under a list.
combineAll(aList)って書くよ。
Now the contextual argument here does two things.
ここでコンテキスト引数が2つのことをする。
First of all, if we don't pass the combinator here and the compiler cannot really find anything,
まず、Combinatorを渡さなくてコンパイラが何も見つけられない場合、
then this code will not compile at all.
このコードはコンパイルできないんだ。
Because the compiler cannot really inject the combinator logic for combineAll.
コンパイラがcombineAllにCombinatorのロジックを注入できないからね。
So if I try to run this application or even compile it, we will see a compiler error saying
アプリケーションを実行したりコンパイルしようとすると、コンパイルエラーが出て、
no implicit argument of type combinator int was found for parameter whatever.
「Combinator[Int]型のimplicit引数が見つかりません」って言われるよ。
All right.
そう。
So we don't have a given instance for the compiler to inject automatically here.
コンパイラが自動的に注入できるgivenインスタンスがないんだ。
Thankfully, if I define a given instance, let's call this int combinator as a combinator int.
でも大丈夫、givenインスタンスを定義すればいい。intCombinatorっていう名前で
And I'm going to define a new combinator.
Combinator[Int]として定義しよう。
And I'm going to define a new combinator real quick.
新しいCombinatorをさっと定義するよ。
So I'm going to say a new combinator int.
new Combinator[Int]って書いて、
And I'm going to say override combine and I'm going to return x plus y.
override def combineでx + yを返すようにする。
Then the compiler will automatically pass this one here.
そうすると、コンパイラがこれを自動的に渡してくれるよ。
So int combinator will actually be passed by the compiler automatically.
intCombinatorがコンパイラによって自動的に渡されるんだ。
In fact, you can also check IntelliJ because it shows you implicit hints.
IntelliJでも確認できるよ。implicit hintsを表示してくれるからね。
That is all the given instances that are automatically passed by the compiler.
コンパイラが自動的に渡すすべてのgivenインスタンスが見えるんだ。
So you can go here to help and search for implicit hints.
HelpメニューからImplicit Hintsを検索してみて。
And here you have a menu here under view.
Viewの下にメニューがあるよ。
And if you click that one, it'll show you what values the compiler automatically passes for you.
クリックすると、コンパイラが自動的に渡す値が表示されるよ。
So right now, if I hit on recompile.
じゃあリコンパイルしよう。
So I'm going to hit command shift 9 here to recompile my code.
Command + Shift + 9でコードをリコンパイルするよ。
Notice that the code can now compile.
コードがコンパイルできるようになったね。
And I can also print, for example, the sum.
合計をprintlnすると、
And the sum, because I have elements 1, 2, 3, 4 in whatever order, the sum should be 10.
要素が1、2、3、4でどんな順番でも、合計は10になるはず。
Because this combinator will sum them all together.
このCombinatorが全部足し合わせてくれるからね。
So we're seeing the number 10 here in the console.
コンソールに10が表示されてるよ。
So a contextual argument can be specified using the using keyword here in a separate argument list.
つまりコンテキスト引数は、usingキーワードを使って別の引数リストで指定できる。
And you can automatically pass or make the compiler pass a particular instance of,
そして呼び出し側のスコープにgivenインスタンスを置くことで、
in this case, combinator int with a given instance in the scope of the call site.
この場合Combinator[Int]の特定のインスタンスをコンパイラに自動的に渡させることができるんだ。
And as you saw earlier, if the compiler cannot really find a given instance to inject here in the using clause,
さっき見たように、コンパイラがusing句に注入するgivenインスタンスが見つからなければ、
then the code will not compile.
コードはコンパイルできない。
And I'm going to show you where the compiler actually looks for given instances.
じゃあ、コンパイラがgivenインスタンスをどこで探すか教えるね。
So first of all, the compiler looks in the local scope.
まず、コンパイラはローカルスコープを探す。
So in the scope where the actual method taking a contextual argument is being called,
コンテキスト引数を取るメソッドが実際に呼ばれているスコープで、
the compiler will search for a particular given value of that type in the scope where that method is called.
コンパイラはその型のgiven値をそのスコープ内で探すんだ。
This is called local scope.
これがローカルスコープ。
The compiler then looks for the imported scope.
次にコンパイラはインポートされたスコープを探す。
Because you can import given instances by using import and then you can write your package.
givenインスタンスはimportでインポートできるよ。パッケージ名を書いて、
And then you can say given after that.
その後にgivenって付ける。
So when you say import your package.given, you import all the given instances from that package.
import パッケージ名.givenって書くと、そのパッケージの全givenインスタンスがインポートされる。
So the compiler will look in the imported scope for the given instances of that type.
コンパイラはインポートされたスコープからもその型のgivenインスタンスを探すよ。
And the third place that compiler will look is the companions.
3番目にコンパイラが探すのはコンパニオンだ。
That is the companion objects, the companion singleton instances of all the types involved in the method call.
つまりメソッド呼び出しに関係するすべての型のコンパニオンオブジェクト、コンパニオンシングルトンインスタンスだね。
And in our particular case, the compiler will look for a default combinator int,
この場合、このメソッド呼び出しで整数のリストを使ってるから、
because we're using a list of integers here in this method call.
コンパイラはデフォルトのCombinator[Int]を探す。
So it will look in the companion of list and the companion of int,
具体的にはListのコンパニオンとIntのコンパニオンを探すよ。
which just so happens that it is the case here for a list.sorted.
list.sortedの場合もまさにこれが起きてるんだ。
So in the exception of me creating a given ordering int here in the scope where the sorted method is being called,
このスコープでgiven Ordering[Int]を作らなかった場合、
the compiler will look in this third place, in the companion of list, which doesn't really have an ordering int,
コンパイラはこの3番目の場所、つまりListのコンパニオンを探すけど、そこにはOrdering[Int]はない。
but rather it looks in the companion of the int type itself, which happens to have an ordering of int.
でもInt型自体のコンパニオンを探して、そこにOrdering[Int]があるんだ。
So the compiler will simply fetch that ordering of int and it will inject it here in the sorted method.
だからコンパイラはそのOrdering[Int]を取得して、sortedメソッドに注入するってわけ。
So quite a lot of power and quite a lot of behavior change depending on the context of the call site.
呼び出し側のコンテキストによって振る舞いがこんなに変わるなんて、すごいパワーだよね。
That's why they're called contextual abstractions.
だからコンテキスト抽象って呼ばれるんだ。
And this is called an abstraction because you're abstracting away.
「抽象」っていうのは、抽象化してるから。
You're basically not thinking of the combinator logic at the call site.
呼び出し側でCombinatorのロジックのことを考えなくていいんだ。
You're simply calling combine all a list and the compiler is only taking care of the rest.
ただcombineAll(リスト)って呼ぶだけで、残りはコンパイラがやってくれる。
So you don't have to care about it, you don't have to think about it.
気にする必要も、考える必要もないんだよ。
Right, let's talk about context bounds.
よし、コンテキスト境界（context bounds）の話をしよう。
Now, there is a shorthand way of using a contextual argument if you're not actually using the combinator instance.
Combinatorインスタンスを直接使わない場合、コンテキスト引数の省略記法があるんだ。
So for example, I can define another method, let's call this combine all, I'm going to use v2 here,
例えば別のメソッドを定義しよう。combineAllV2にして、
with type argument a and a list as a list of a.
型引数Aでlist: List[A]を取る。
And if you're not actually using the combinator instance directly, but you're rather calling other methods that are using a combinator a,
Combinatorインスタンスを直接使わないで、Combinator[A]を使う他のメソッドを呼ぶだけなら、
then you can simply say using combinator a, not necessarily naming that particular instance.
using Combinator[A]って書くだけで、そのインスタンスに名前を付ける必要はないよ。
And this will return an a and the implementation can be whatever.
戻り値はAで、実装は何でもいい。
And in that case, there's also an even more shorthand notation for specifying a using clause,
さらに、using句にはもっと短い記法もあるんだ。
because you're only mentioning that you need a combinator a so that the compiler can use it,
Combinator[A]が必要ってことだけをコンパイラに伝えれば、
but you don't necessarily have to name it.
名前を付ける必要はない。
So this is only a type restriction for the compiler.
これはコンパイラのための型制約にすぎないんだ。
So you can say combinator or combine all.
だからcombineAll、
I'm going to use v3 here with the type argument a and list as a list of a and this returns an a.
V3にしよう。型引数Aでlist: List[A]を取ってAを返す。
The implementation can be whatever.
実装は何でもいい。
And in order to mark to the compiler that you need a combinator a in scope,
コンパイラにCombinator[A]がスコープに必要だと伝えるために、
where this combine all v3 method is going to be called,
このcombineAllV3が呼ばれるスコープでCombinator[A]を
you only need to type restriction to a so that the compiler can find a combinator a in scope.
見つけられるように、Aに型制約を付ければいいんだ。
So the marker is a colon combinator.
そのマーカーは A: Combinator って書く。
Now, when you read real life skull code and your project were at your job,
実際のScalaのコードで、型引数の後にコロンと何かの型が書いてあったら、
and you see a method that takes a type argument and then say colon some type,
「Aにはスコープ内にCombinator[A]の
then that should be read as a marker a must have a given instance of combiner or combinator a in scope.
givenインスタンスが必要」って読むんだよ。
So a colon combinator is identical to this other method definition that I wrote above.
つまりA: Combinatorは、上に書いたメソッド定義と同じ意味なんだ。
So I think you got the idea.
理解できたかな。
A colon combinator is a form of type restriction.
A: Combinatorは型制約の一種だよ。
Let me tell you where context arguments are useful.
コンテキスト引数がどこで役立つか教えるね。
So they're useful for a variety of patterns in functional programming and in the Scala language in general.
関数型プログラミングやScala言語全般のさまざまなパターンで役立つよ。
Type classes are a massive use case for contextual arguments.
型クラス（type class）はコンテキスト引数の最大のユースケースだ。
And type classes are an advanced feature of functional programming in general.
型クラスは関数型プログラミングの高度な機能で、
And they're quite outside the scope of this video.
この動画の範囲外だけどね。
I have a bunch more on my YouTube channel.
YouTubeチャンネルにもっとたくさん動画があるよ。
Then we have dependency injection.
あと依存性注入（DI）もある。
We have contextual abstractions for using code for some types but not for others.
一部の型では使えて他の型では使えないコードのためのコンテキスト抽象もある。
So context dependent functionality.
コンテキスト依存の機能ってやつだね。
That is the capability of restricting a piece of your logic to some types but not for others,
つまり、givenインスタンスの有無によって、
depending on the contextual presence of given instances.
特定の型だけにロジックを制限できる能力なんだ。
And also a quite magical aspect of the Scala language which is type level programming.
それと、Scala言語のかなり魔法的な側面である型レベルプログラミングもある。
Then type level programming is a capability exhibited by the Scala language in which
型レベルプログラミングはScala言語の能力で、
the compiler can generate types and prove relationships between types at compile time.
コンパイラがコンパイル時に型を生成したり、型同士の関係を証明したりできるんだ。
This is very very powerful and also quite abstract.
これは非常に強力で、かなり抽象的でもある。
And contextual arguments provide the vehicle for achieving that.
コンテキスト引数がそれを実現するための手段を提供するんだよ。
Alright, so we've talked a lot about contextual arguments.
さて、コンテキスト引数についてたくさん話したね。
Let's talk about the second part of this video on contextual abstractions.
この動画の2つ目のパート、コンテキスト抽象の続きを話そう。
And that is extension methods.
拡張メソッド（extension methods）だよ。
Now, the truth is that in the Scala language you can add additional methods to a type.
実はScalaでは、型が定義された後からでもメソッドを追加できるんだ。
After it was defined, even if you have no control over the source of that type.
その型のソースコードに手を出せなくてもね。
And extension methods are heavily used in functional programming libraries such as cats or cats effect.
拡張メソッドはCatsやCats Effectみたいな関数型プログラミングライブラリで頻繁に使われるよ。
And let me give an example.
例を見せるね。
Let me define a case class.
case classを定義しよう。
So case class person with a name.
case class PersonでnameフィールドをStringで持つ。
And this class has a simple method.
このクラスにはシンプルなメソッドがあって、
Let's call this greet.
greetって名前にしよう。
So greet will return a string and say,
greetはStringを返して、こう言う。
"Hi, my name is name.
「Hi, my name is $name.
I love Scala."
I love Scala!」
Of course, I love Scala is optional.
もちろん「I love Scala」はオプションだけどね。
I hope you do.
みんなもScala好きだといいな。
And after that, I'm going to create a particular structure that you have not seen in this course yet.
この後、このコースではまだ見たことのない構造を作るよ。
And I'm going to write the following.
こう書くんだ。
I'm going to say extension, which is a contextual keyword in the Scala grammar.
extensionって書く。これはScalaの文法におけるコンテキストキーワードだよ。
And I'm going to say extension string as a string.
extension (string: String) って書く。
And I'm going to define a method called greet, which returns a string.
そしてgreetっていうメソッドを定義して、Stringを返す。
And the implementation of this method is going to be new person without string dot greet.
実装はnew Person(string).greetにするよ。
Now, this particular structure will then allow me to write, for example,
この構造があると、例えばこう書けるようになる。
Daniel's greeting as the string Daniel dot greet.
danielsGreetingとして、文字列"Daniel".greetって書ける。
Just like that.
こんな感じ。
As if greet was part of the string Daniel.
まるでgreetが文字列"Daniel"のメソッドであるかのようにね。
Obviously, if I had not written this piece with extension string string,
もちろん、このextensionの部分を書いてなかったら、
then if I try compiling my code, then the greet method will not be found.
コンパイルしようとするとgreetメソッドが見つからない。
Because greet does not belong to the string class.
greetはStringクラスのメソッドじゃないからね。
But if I write this structure here with an extension,
でもこのextensionの構造を書いておけば、
then I will compile my code and it will compile just fine.
コードをコンパイルすると問題なくコンパイルできる。
And the reason is that the compiler normally would not compile the greet call on the string Daniel,
理由は、コンパイラは普通なら文字列"Daniel"に対するgreetの呼び出しをコンパイルできないけど、
but it would search for all possible extension methods on the string type.
String型に対する全ての拡張メソッドを探してくれるからなんだ。
And because I created an extension to the string type,
String型にextensionを作ったから、
it will have access to this greet method, which I added later to the string class.
後からStringクラスに追加したこのgreetメソッドにアクセスできるんだよ。
And this gives enormous power.
これはものすごいパワーだよ。
And that is because we can enhance existing classes to suit our needs.
既存のクラスを自分のニーズに合わせて拡張できるからね。
And this is called type enrichment.
これは型エンリッチメント（type enrichment）って呼ばれるよ。
And colloquially in Scala 2, that was called pimping a type.
Scala 2の時代には口語的に「型のpimping」って呼ばれてたんだ。
Now, the term pimping went out of fashion.
まあpimpingって言い方は廃れたけどね。
And this more boring type enrichment term was a little bit more prevalent in the Scala literature.
もうちょっと地味な型エンリッチメントって用語の方がScalaの文献では一般的になったよ。
So we have this notion of type enrichment through extension methods on existing types.
既存の型への拡張メソッドによる型エンリッチメントっていう概念だね。
Now, you can also add generic extension methods.
ジェネリックな拡張メソッドも追加できるよ。
So we can, for example, create a method to combine all the elements on a particular list,
例えば、特定のリストの全要素を結合するメソッドを作って、
as if the combine all method belonged to the list type.
あたかもそのメソッドがList型に最初から属してるかのようにできるんだ。
And at the same time, this feature of extension methods in Scala can also be combined with contextual parameters,
さらにScalaの拡張メソッドは、コンテキストパラメータと組み合わせることもできて、
with great success and a lot of expressiveness and power.
これがすごい表現力とパワーを生むんだ。
So I can define extension, which takes a type argument a.
extension[A]って書いて、型引数Aを取る。
So considering a type a and a list as a list of a.
型AとしてlistをList[A]として受け取る。
Then I can define a method.
そしてメソッドを定義する。
Let's call this combine all.
combineAllにしよう。
But I'm going to say combine all values so that we don't really have a name collision with this other combine all method.
ただし、さっきのcombineAllと名前が被らないようにcombineAllValuesにするよ。
And combine all values will take a contextual argument.
combineAllValuesはコンテキスト引数を取る。
So using combinator as a combinator a.
using combinator: Combinator[A]だね。
And this will return an a.
戻り値はA。
And I can write the same implementation.
実装は同じものが使えるよ。
So list dot reduce with combinator dot combine.
list.reduce(combinator.combine)って書く。
Now with this little piece of code, then I can say val, let's call this the sum version 2.
このちょっとしたコードで、valを定義しよう。sumV2にして、
I can then say a list dot combine all values.
aList.combineAllValuesって書ける。
Just like that.
これだけでOK。
So I can recompile my code and the code will work just as fine.
リコンパイルすると問題なく動くよ。
And if I do print line the sum v2, then we're still going to see the number 10 to the console.
sumV2をprintlnすると、やっぱりコンソールに10が表示される。
So we have it here.
ほら、ここに出てるね。
So notice how powerful our APIs can be.
APIがどれだけパワフルになるか注目してね。
They seem as though they always belongs to the list class in this case.
まるでずっとListクラスに属してたかのように見えるでしょ。
And also combining the power of contextual arguments.
しかもコンテキスト引数のパワーも合わせると、
That will make for a very expressive and powerful set of APIs and language.
非常に表現力豊かでパワフルなAPIと言語になるんだ。
Now contextual abstractions are an advanced set of features.
コンテキスト抽象は高度な機能セットだよ。
And there are other forms of contextual abstractions that's called support,
Scalaがサポートする他の形式のコンテキスト抽象もあって、
such as defining and inferring type classes, implicit conversions, or contextual function types.
型クラスの定義と推論、暗黙の型変換、コンテキスト関数型なんかがあるよ。
A bit outside the scope of this video.
この動画の範囲からはちょっと外れるけどね。
But I'm going to cover them in the advanced Scala course due shortly.
近々出るAdvanced Scalaコースでカバーする予定だよ。
So I hope you enjoyed this video and waiting for you in the Rock the JVM website,
この動画を楽しんでくれたなら嬉しいな。Rock the JVMのウェブサイト、
in the courses, and on the Rock the JVM YouTube channel.
コース、そしてRock the JVMのYouTubeチャンネルで待ってるよ。
I'm Daniel, signing off.
Danielでした。またね。